Guide to the Arthur Ovaska papers 1888-2000
Arthur Ovaska papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Arthur Ovaska papers. 1888-2000, bulk 1970-1990.
15-2-4329
Arthur, Ovaska, 1951-.
9.2 cubic feet.
18 mapcase folders.
Drawings, plans.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Drawings and plans from competitions, students, and Ovaska's work as a professional and student.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Arthur Ovaska received his Bachelor of Architecture degree at Cornell University in 1974. After receiving his undergraduate degree at Cornell, Ovaska began graduate architecture studies with his mentor, professor and department chair O. M. Ungers. From 1974 to 1978, he collaborated with Ungers in Ithaca and Koand#x308;ln, Germany. Founded the office of Kollhoff andamp; Ovaska in Berlin in 1978 with Hans Kollhoff. Ovaska left Berlin in 1987 to accept a full-time academic position at Cornell. His career included appointments as director of undergraduate studies, director of graduate studies, and chair of the Department of Architecture.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Drawings and plans from competitions, students, and Ovaska's work as a professional and student.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ovaska, Arthur, 1951-.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Competition
Series II. Working Drawings
Series III. Work as Student
Series IV. Posters
Series V. Work and miscellaneous
Series VI. Maps
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Competition
  - Berlin Museum ERW, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    11x17 printed packet of final drawings, photocopies. Larger set of printed drawings, mixed with original sketches / working drawings, ink on trace paper
  - Salem, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Collection of research and competition materials for the Salem Witch Trials Tercentenary Memorial Competition Program May 1991
    Set of brochures for historic tours in Salem area
    Chapter book, titled, The Devil in Massachusetts by Marion L. Starkey
    Question/Answer sheet for questions about the competition
    Site maps and photos (photocopies)
    Volumes I and II of The Witchcraft Hysteria of 1692 by Leo Bonfanti
  - Chapter book, titled, The Devil in Massachusetts by Marion L. Starkey, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Berlin Museum Extension, 1980-1989 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Large collection of original process drawings and sketches, pencil/ink on trace - Prints of fnal drawings (S); Final drawings, pencil on thick card stock paper;B/W photographs of site; Misc. items: NYTimes page, lecture advertisement, work from Welfare Island; Student projects by A.Ovaska
  - Miscellaneous sketches, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 4)
    A miscellaneous collection of what appears to be one project. Most sketches are in plan and suggest site analysis / plan arrangement studies. Map of Berlin, prints.
  - Moscow, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 6)
    Collection of sketches: Ink on trace paper, Ink on cardstock. Smaller folder 8.5x11 photocopies of a figure ground map, site.
  - Berlin Museum Extension, 1988-1989 (Mapcase-folder 8)
    Presentation boards for Berlin Museum Extension competition: small-scale prints of original drawings mounted on cardstock; study drawings, pencil on vellum; shadow study; Map of site
  - Cornell Project, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 11)
    Working drawings for proposed renovation of AAP Facilities project; Sketches - ink on trace paper / vellum; Primarily plan and axonometric studies
  - Berlin Museum Garten, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 12)
    Contains a set of original drawings and presentation-quality prints for the Berlin Museum Garten, possibly curated for a lecture at Syracuse University.
    Presentation boards for Berlin Museum Extension competition - for exhibition (?) depicting precedent studies of various gardens (prints), as well as 1-2 original drawings of the project pasted onto card stock.
    Study drawings in plan, originals, pen on newsprint paper. Set of trace paper sketches, ink on trace paper/newsprint.
    Set of vellum prints, of plan drawing/axon/perspectives.
    An extensive collection of drawings related to the Berlin Museum Garden - a combination of originals, prints
  - Berlin Museum Garden Sketches, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 14)
    Set of unlabeled sketches, ink on trace paper, relating to Berlin Museum garden. 2 maps of site, Berlin, Some colored
  - Set of presentation boards for Berlin Museum Garden, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 15)
    Shadow plan drawings, with precedent gardens included on sides. Section / elevation drawings, prints with original colored pencil work.
    Board 01-A: Plan/Axonometric drawing of garden proposal, flanked on both sides by drawings/prints of historic precedent garden projects.
    Board 01-B: Shadow plan of garden project, labeled Berlin Museum Garden, M 1:200.
    Board 01-C: Shadow plan of garden project with labeled programmatic zones /building elements / section cut lines, text on right side, labeled Berlin Museum Garten, M 1:200
  - Set of presentation boards for Berlin Museum Garden, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 16)
    Board 01-D: 3 Elevation drawings, showing front elevation of Berlin Museum and 2 side elevations of the garden project, labeled Ansicht Lindenstrasse, Schnitt NN, and Schnitt M-M respectively, original colored pencil work over print.
    Board 01-E: 3 section drawings through garden project, labeled Schnitt H-H, Schnitt J-J, and Schnitt K-K, original colored pencil work over print.
    Board 01 - F: Longitudinal section drawing through Berlin museum and garden project proposal, original colored pencil work over print, labeled BMG: Berlin Museum Garten, Internat Bauasstellung 1984, Schmitt AA, Kolhoff and Ovaska.
    Board 01 - G: Technical plan drawing of garden proposal, original colored pencil work over print, annotated with ground heights and dimensions, labeled BMG: Berlin Museum Garden, Internat Bauasstellung 1984, Vermessungsplan
  - Welfare Island: competition submission for an urban design plan for Roosevelt Island, Undated; 1
    Urban Scale, complete drawing set including Plans, axons, diagrams. Possibly collaborative work with OM Ungers
  - Berlin Neuenberg St. Base, 2
    Multiple maps of Berlin, original drawings, all text in German.
  - Hamburg: Deichtor and Ericus, Undated; 4
    Maps of Hamburg, full drawing set, all text in German. All labelled: Stadtebaulicher Idennweftbewerb Deichtor und Ericus.
  - A.Ovaska, Berlin Address (Sportparkplatz), Undated; 11
    Part of Sportparkplatz competition, two original drawings
  - Savannah, Date Unknown; 11
    1 site plan of Savannah, original line drawing, ink on paper; 2 figure ground maps of Savannah, prints
  - Berlin, 1987; 11
    Maps of Berlin, prints on vellum, scale 1:500; Complete drawing set - plans, sections, elevations, prints on paper; All drawings labeled Wettbewerb, Lützowplatz, Berlin, Südliches Tiergartenviertel, Bauausstellung Berlin GmBH 1987"
  - Sportparkplatz Wil. Original Competition Submission, Date Unknown; 9
    Prints of hand drawings on paper; Complete drawing set of competition submission, primarily plan drawings; Perspective section drawings (cross/longitudinal)
  - Sportparkplatz Originals, Date Unknown; 9
    Original drawing set for Sportparkplatz competition, ink on vellum. Contains some prints.
  - Housing Development Competition for Kita am Dennewitzpark, Date Unknown; 13
    2 Maps of Berlin; Collection of trace paper sketches, Elevation drawings of various house facade typologies
    (6) map/site plans of Berlin, prints, 1 aerial photograph plan, all labeled Der senator for Bau-und Wohnungswesen BERLIN, Bauwettbewerb Wohnbebauung ung Kita am Dennewitzpark (housing development competition).
    Complete drawing set for competition
  - Competition Diplomatenvier, Date Unknown; 16
    Extensive collection of process drawings, no final drawings. All contents wrapped in label reading: BMG Erweiterung: Skizzen, Unterlagen.
    Aerial photograph map of Sudliches Tiergartenviertel
  - Sportpakplatz Competition submission boards, Date Unknown; 18
    Set of 5 prints: Plans, sections, and written description of design proposal for Sportparkplatz competition
    Draft boards for competition (?)
    All text in German
  - Kammergericht Axon Bleistift, Date Unknown; 19
    1 pencil axon drawing on trace paper - Large, process work
  - BMG Erweiterung Axon, Date Unknown; 19
    1 Axonometric drawing, original ink on paper, freehand. Depicts site with intervention attached
  - Long trace paper sketches, Date Unknown; 21
    Extremely large, long trace paper sketches, in axon, of an urban planning project, ink on trace paper
    Some smaller sketches, depicting site plan, ink/colored pencil on trace paper
    1 sketch annotated with; CA 10 different sport activities, 10 playing felds for football, volleyball, badminton, etc. / playgrounds for children or different age groups / integrated leisure area, picnic area (grilling, coffee, fre)
  - Berlin Maps/Sketches, 11
    Map of Berlin, print on vellum
    Set of trace paper sketches.
    Seemingly related to the contents of Tube 21, ink on trace paper, primarily in plan
  - Skizzen Platz der Republik, 23
    Large Collection of sketches, all ink on trace paper
    Sketches all in plan
  - Savannah, Date Unknown; 25
    Compilation of site research done about Savannah, Georgia.
    Water supply / sanitary sewage lines plan drawing, prepared by Central of Georgia Railway water supply fre protection and sanitary sewer lines and shore and upper yard of Savannah, Georgia
    Map / site plan of Savannah, line drawing, print
    Aerial photograph map of Chatham County, Georgia, photo date March 1985
    1:400 map/site plan of Savannah
    Map of Savannah, on glossy paper, labeled 1991 Average Daily Traffic Counts for Chatham County - Savannah, Georgia, June 1992
  - Holocaust Memorial, Date Unknown; 25
    Site map of the location of competition designs and elevations of buildings on nearby streets, labeled The New England Holocaust Memorial Competition, Plan, 1:20
    Site plan of greater context
    Collection of trace paper sketches, ink/pencil on trace paper, primarily in plan
    photocopies of site, etc. Original pencil drawings on vellum, not labeled
- Series II. Working Drawings
  - Welfare Island: working drawings for competition, Date Unknown; 1
    Pencil and ink on trace paper and vellum.
  - Working drawings, 1996; 21
    Collection of sketches, ink on trace paper
    Map of Ithaca East Quadrangle published by the NY Geological Survey
    Site plans, prints, labeled Village of Plainfeld Town Center Design Competition dated Oct 1996
    Working drawings for town center design competition
    plans, site plans, zoning maps, trace paper sketches, elevation studies. etc.
- Series III. Work as Student
  - Watkins Glen, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Stack of working drawings, sketches, and research (newspaper articles, maps, print-outs) for Watkins Glen Graduate Design Studio 1974 by A.Ovaska. Some prints of final drawings
  - Miscellaneous sketches, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 2-3)
    A miscellaneous collection of what appears to be 4 different projects, separated by plain sheets of paper. All contents are trace paper sketches or constructed drawings - NO labels, dates, or identifying info
  - 4th year Design Studio, 1972 (Mapcase-folder 5)
    Complete final drawing set (ink on vellum) from 4th year design studio 1972; JA Wells, work by A.Ovaska; Rolling Home project; Final drawings, some sketches / study drawings.
    Housing project - a few misc. drawings - plans, axonometric, with OM Ungers.
  - Miscellaneous sketches, Date Unknown; 1970-1973 (Mapcase-folder 7)
    Collection of work by A.Ovaska as a student, including: Design 106 (Ithaca City Hall), Design 102 (Stock Brokerage Office), Design 205 (Warehouse).
    Final presentation boards from Design 102 - prints mounted on cardboard.
    Printed maps of Ithaca / site plan from Design 106.
    Print of axonometric drawings, Design 106.
    Miscellaneous collection of trace paper sketches.
    Lecture/Exhibition poster labeled Cornell Architecture Faculty 1971 Buildings and Projects, AD White Museum of Art. Exhibition/Lecture poster titled Rational Architecture: The Architecture of a City, the Architectural Association. Set of prints/posters titled Rationalismo (all text in Italian), depicting various housing typologies.
  - Work as Student, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 17)
    Set of presentation boards from Design Studio 104, work by A.Ovaska.
    Board 03 - A: Site shadow plan drawing, labeled RH-BD, Row-House Block Development, Site Plan (Ground Plane), Ovaska 104, May 19th, 1971.
    Board 03 - B: North and West section/elevation drawings, labeled RH-BD, Elevations, Sections Ovaska 104.
    Board 03 - C: Axonometric drawing of project, projected from plan, labeled RHBD, Site Axonometric, Ovaska 104.
    Board 03 - D: Plan drawings depicting of units Type A, Type B, and Type C, 2 perspective drawings of interior, labeled RH-BD, Plans, Unit Types, Ovaska 104.
    Board 03 - E: Axonometric drawing of structural diagram, labeled with Spring Shut Doors, Removable Bottom for Cleaning - held in place by clamps.
  - Design 103 1970, Prof. Cohen, "Crafts Museum" original drawings by A.Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - Design 104, "Row House" original drawings by A.Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - Design 105, "North Campus Housing" original drawings by A.Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - Tech. 601, "Beach Shelter" 10.15.1970, original drawings by A.Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - Design 106 "City Hall" original drawings by A.Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - DWG 511 May, original drawings by A.Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - ARCH 205, Warehouse, original drawings by A.Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - Unlabelled miscellaneous drawings by Ovaska, 1970-1974; 6
  - Originals Craft Museum, 1970; 6
    Design 103, professor Cohen; Complete drawing set, original drawings ink on vellum; Plans, sections, elevation, axon; Project for the design of a museum
  - Gotham City, Date Unknown; 6
    Original collage from Gotham City project drawing.
    Print of Gotham City collage with original coloring work.
    Work produced from a summer studio taught with OM Ungers and Werner Goehner.
    2 maps of NYC (prints)
  - Graduate Studio Watkins, 1974; 8
    Student project by A.Ovaska titled Watkins Glen - Highway Experiment, 1974 Graduate Studio A.Ovaska.
    Complete drawing set - plan, axonometric, diagrams (L)Misc. site plan, original color work on a B/W axonometric drawing, prints.
    Misc. trace paper sketches.
    Printed plan of Christ Church Oxford and original ink on vellum, drawing of a proposed intervention on the Great Quadrangle
  - Graduate Studio Watkins Glen, 1974; 10
    Original drawings, ink on vellum, some colored. Includes process work drawings, sketches
  - Work as Student, 1970; 22
    Large misc collection of student work by A.Ovaska. Primarily original drawings, ink on vellum
    Includes work from: Arch 205, Design 103 (Crafts Museum), Design 104, Design 105 (Ithaca City Hall), Tech 601, etc.
    Combination of working and final drawings
  - Watkins Glen Highway Experiment, 1974; 24
    1 drawing, section and shadow elevation, final drawing, original ink on paper, labeled Watkins Glen - Highway Experiment Section Type 1, AA Ovaska Conell University Graduate Studio May 1974
- Series IV. Posters
  - Assorted posters, 1970-1980; 2
    US Army recruitment, OM Ungers lecture posters titled "Design with Morphologies", PUMP
  - Assorted posters, Date Unknown; 5
    (2) S colorful graphic calendar posters for Feb and March; S army poster advertising C-54 Douglas airplane; Poster labeled "Orskliche Ausicht depicting extremely detailed elevation drawing of the Cathedral of Cologne (?) - artist credited as "Franz Schmitz, Der Dom zu Köln, Köln und Neub 1868-1879, Tafel 7; All text in German; (Duplicate) PUMP - Cornell student publication, newspaper satire
  - Assorted posters, Date Unknown; 5
    Photographiez! Kodak poster, advertising Ektachrome film, depicting 12 different versions of the same image of a tree in the landscape.
    Black and white, High resolution photo of feet, titled 278 Feet, Personality Posters Inc 1967 - (XL) b/w photo of hairy monster face, Personality Posters Inc 1967.
    Exhibition poster, "Nekropolis, Michael Ruetz, 100 Photographien 1968-1976, all text in German.
    Lecture series poster, Berliner Sommerakademie für Architektur" Jun-July 1977, all text in German.
    Lecture series poster, "2. Berliner Sommerakademie für Architektur Gestaltung öffentlicher Räume" Jun-July 1978, text in German.
    Exhibition Poster, "Garten in Geschichte und Gegenwart" (Gardens in the past and present) 13.8-1.9.1978, text In German.
  - Assorted posters, Date Unknown; 15
    Procol Harum band poster; Das Belvedere des Prinzen Eugen in Wein 1714-1723 Johann Lucas von Hildebrandt poster depicting hand-drawn scenes.
    Karl Friedrich Schinkel 1781-1841 poster depicting hand-drawn architectural works, 3 copies.
    Set of 4 Le Corbusier posters, depicting a timeline of his works
  - Glossy, colored print painting titled "Cahokia Mounds" by AL Townsend, Date Unknown; 19
  - Assorted posters, Date Unknown; 20
    Colorful Bob Dylan poster
    Colorful poster advertising Fly SAS to Switzerland
    Set of posters depicting national parks
  - Train posters, Date Unknown; 24
    2 posters advertising the New Haven Railroad
    1 Labeled Train Travelers May eat in Diner or Grill Car, The New Haven RR, Serving New York and the Great Industrial States of Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Connecticut
    1 Labeled Rest and Relaxation at Night in Modern Sleeping CarsRed/white lettering, overlaid on b/w photograph of train passengers in a dining car
  - Posters, 1988; 24
    Preston H. Thomas Memorial Lecture Series, 1988
    Robin Evans, Geometry in and Around Architecture
  - Aalto, Date Unknown; 24
    1 poster depicting a wall covering for an auditorium (?) by Aalto, Glossy paper, Labeled Helsingin Konserttitalo, Vasen Snuseina, Alvar Aalto Arkkitehti
  - Exhibition: Golden Oldies, Date Unknown; 30
    Poster from Golden Oldies exhibition and drawing set of A.Ovaskaâs project from Design 106
    prints on newspaper, possibly the project that was chosen to be exhibited (?)
    Labeled Golden Oldies: Faculty as Students Show, East Sibley Corridor, 1946 1978, Cornell University Department of Architecture, Middling Reception Dragon Day 1987 11:00am, Sibley Hall
    Participants names listed on poster, including: Michael Cohen, Michael Dennis, Werner Goehner, George Hascup, Lee Hodgden, Alexander Kira, Victoria Meyers, John Miller, Leonard Mirin, Vincent Mulcahy, John Ostlund, Arthur Ovaska, John Shaw, Andrea Simitch, Val Warke, Jerry Wells, John Zissovici
  - 2 Lecture posters advertising lectures by A.Ovaska at Savannah College of Art and Design (SCAD), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Lenne and Schinkel in the Potsdam Landscape: Place Making Precedent, by Arthur Ovaska, Eichberg 304, SCAD Architecture
    Reconstruction: A Future Context for the Past, a Lecture by Arthur Ovaska, SCAD
  - Posters, Date Unknown (Mapcase-folder 10)
    Exhibition poster titled "Syracuse University School of Architecture". Exhibition, the Berlin Museum Garden, Arthur A. Ovaska with Hans Kolhoff, multiple copies. Exhibition poster titled "BYGGTÍBERLÍN, sýning í ásmundarsal, fyrirlestrar í odda Arthur Ovaska og Hildebrand Machleid" all text in Icelandic, referring to a lecture about built works in Berlin. Exhibition poster titled "Modern Houses: A Documentation", Arch 152 Spring 1989, Hartell Gallery, professors Ovaska and Simitch; Lecture poster titled Arthur Ovaska: Urban Realizations in Berlin 1978-1988, Building in a Modern Context for Historical Mementos or ‘There aren’t no ‘There’ There,’ Cornell Architecture, February 1988. 2 misc. site plans; 1 map of Plymouth County
- Series V. Work and miscellaneous
  - Moscow, Undated; 3
    Site plans of Moscow, original drawings and some prints. Ink on vellum.
  - Tribeca Housing Project/Lower Manhattan, 1975; 7
    Appears to be a public housing proposal: multiple maps of lower Manhattan, all labeled "Office of Lower Manhattan Development"; original drawings of proposed project
  - Student work by Monika Saras, 2000; 3
    Original drawings, complete set, ink/graphite on vellum
  - Berlin Museum Extension, 1988-1989; 12
    Printed map of site in Berlin; 5 original drawings, ink on vellum, freehanded
  - Berlin Museum Garten, Date Unknown; 12
    Complete drawing set, primarily plan drawings; Stamped by Kolhoff and Ovaska Architekten; Mostly prints, 1 original drawing
  - Cornell, 1988; 8
    Proposed plans for extension for AAP Facilities/Campus; 2 schemes: C and D; Longitudinal sections through Sibley Dome, Fine Arts library area included; Plan of Arts Quad (photocopy print); Topographic map of surrounding site. A collaboration with Werner Goehner
  - Adenauer Platz Potsdam Base DWGs, Undated; 10
    Plan drawings, prints; Base drawings for site research
  - Prelim Welfare Island and Misc, Date Unknown; 15
    Collection of trace paper sketches, preliminary ideas for Welfare Island project; Constructed axonometric drawings, pencil on vellum. All original drawings
  - Savannah, 16
    Set of blueprint maps of the coastline along the Savannah river; Blueprint map of the city of Savannah; packet of old maps of Savannah/site information
  - Various sketches, maps, and drawings, Date Unknown; 17
    Over 40 drawings, sketches, maps. Many axonometric studies, pen on trace paper
    Mixed maps of Manhattan and Berlin.
  - Wassaic, Date Unknown; 19
    1 Map drawings / site plan
    1 shadow plan, original drawing ink on vellum
    1 site plan, print, labeled Wassaic Development Center, Restructuring/Consolidation Study, Amenia NY, Buckhurst Fish Hutton Katz
  - Braunschweig, Date Unknown; 20
    Extensive collection of colored trace paper sketches, ink, colored pencil, graphite
    1 print depicting project, colored in (colored pencil)
    Project for a city in Northern Germany: design for a park depicting earth mounds architecture
  - Hingham, 1980; 23
    4 maps of Eastern Massachusetts, including Hingham, Cohasett, Norwell, etc. - at one time glued together to create 1 larger map
    Set of 4 maps depicting site area, land plots, and subdivision plan of land for Cushing Street Hingham, Mass, labeled From the Offce of Lewis K. Perkins Engr. August 1936 prints
    Map labeled Plan of Land in Hingham Mass made for Andrew Ovaska, April 16, 1946 - reprinted in 1980
  - Thesis, S. Tierg, 18
    Map of Berlin, print
    Map of Berlin, highlighting area labeled Tiergarten
    2 figure-ground maps
    Large collection of hand-drawn maps and floor plans, ink/pencil on trace paper
    Not final drawings - process/research work (?)
    1 map of lower Manhattan, labeled OLMD
  - Site study: Sudl. Tiergarten Thesis, Date Unknown; 21
    2 Maps of Berlin, prints
    Trace paper line drawings isolating sections of Berlin map
    Collection of un-labeled trace paper drawings, ink, of areas of Berlin
    Site analysis
  - Site study: Maps of Berlin, Date Unknown; 25
    Set of Maps of Berlin, prints on Vellum
    Some fragments, some complete maps
    Some axonometric, depicting certain building on map
  - Miscellaneous plans, Date Unknown; 31
    4 original plan drawings, ink on vellum. No labels, dates, or other identifying information. Possibly student work?
  - Rand Hall, Date Unknown; 31
    Large photocopy of an elevation drawing of Rand Hall, labeled Rand Hall Sibley College, North Elevation Scale 1/4, Gibb and Waltz Architects
  - Unlabelled drawing on vellum, Date Unknown; 31
  - Miscellaneous blueprint posters, Date Unknown; 24
    Set of large prints of drawings, on newsprint, blue ink on off-white paper. Depicts plans, sections, elevations, axonometric. Possibly work by A.Ovaska (?), Only label SCB II 64121